hi welcome back to lamrim and that
picture was arya sangha don't forget
uh the the guy with the dog
and i love the picture
it's uh we tend to think that people
like arya sangha must have been very
handsome and
but look you don't spend 12 years in a
cave
and and look like some
handsome llama i mean it's hard work and
probably had a coat like that and
you know so uh and don't forget the
story
that we talked about during the lion
stance
that uh he spent 12 years in the cave
frustrated that he couldn't meet
maitreya
and then when he left the cave
and he found a dying dog on the road
that had been hit by a wagon like a dog
that was hit by a car
and nobody stopped to help the dog
except him
and then suddenly because of that moment
of bodhichitta
he saw my train and then my trainer
taught him okay the lion stance
[Music]
that's the famous lines that maitreya
taught him
okay here we go
uh we're on to benefit or the
the ten cool things
that will happen to you if you get body
tuna and
here's number eight we're starting
number eight which means that no
obstacles can touch you and you know
all of us all of you in this class
okay if you got to the alarm rim class
uh you're serious you're a serious
person this is not a
you know a half somebody told me we
should stick to uh
i don't even forget the name of the
thing tick tock
uh what's the other one
don't go on for more than three minutes
you know two minutes or one minute
this is uh the most people can't handle
right now
so no we're asking you to come to 12
years
or 15 years so if you're in this class
[Music]
you're probably a serious person and
you're probably a very committed person
otherwise you're not going to make it
through 15 years or 20 years of long
room
and if you're a serious person
if you're trying to help people
seriously over a long period of time
like diamond mountain uh has how many
years now
20 basically 20 something years and and
people in this room a lot of them have
been here for 20 years or
some of them and it's a long
job and there's lots of problems
there's just lots of problems you can't
do big things
without problems and it's funny
you know all of us want to do big things
and then we get problems and we start to
well
you know my practice is no good i had a
problem today
come on you know you're going to have
problems up to buddhahood
you know you're going to have problems
there's going to be screw-ups
endless screw-ups the bigger the project
the more screw-ups okay so don't get all
excited about it okay i'll tell you
something
uh i can't remember the name
this morning i couldn't remember the
name
of a person who gave us a lot of trouble
like five years ago
i couldn't remember the name and you
know
and it's not just senility it's that
they just go away you know things happen
problems come and you have a choice you
can quit
or you can keep going and if you're
going to keep going you have another
choice
you can be grumpy about the problems or
you can laugh at them
oh look patio man we tried to make
biochar nick's house
the whole thing wow you know
so you know uh you might as well have
fun
okay and if you have body tenor
then the problems get very small the
problems shrink
fast and you can have fun
even when you're having pretty serious
obstacles and problems
and then you know what happens if you're
having fun
while you have a problem the problem's
not much a problem
okay so here we go uh
i like this picture i don't know this
picture actually disturbing picture of a
tank
okay and they're terrible things
they're really terrible things people
still use them
okay they were invented for world war
one
they were invented in 1916 or 17.
and they started and they found out if
you make a metal box
on wheels you can kill people and
you can be comfortable you can sit
inside the box
and just shoot other people and they
can't shoot you
and you can just roll over in the middle
of the other people's army and
shoot people and they're still popular
they still measure
the strength of an army for example in
europe uh
they they will measure a country's
military strength by how many tanks do
they have
so they're still they're they're still
used a lot
and the point is you can just sit in the
middle of it
and the whole world can be blowing up
around you
and it's it's not comfortable but it's
not bad
okay you're in a metal box and you're
protected
and that's what bodhichitta does for you
okay
uh bodhichitta is like sitting in a tank
in a war
and everybody else is getting blown up
and dying and you're just kind of having
a coffee probably
okay and bodhichitta is like that thing
okay i don't like
tanks i i think they are a symbol of our
failure as
people uh but the idea that they could
protect you
is a good is a nice image okay all right
yes
there's a kind of special karma
[Music]
yeah you real emperor it's a real world
emperor
uh you're called a real um king of the
world
president of the world because you have
the wheel and the wheel is a
spaceship with lots of army guys in it
okay and uh to become a king of the
world
and there's different levels of king of
the world if you took dci course you
know about that
a gold emperor you know they have no
competition
nobody everyone begs them to be king in
the world
they don't have to campaign and they
don't have to threaten anybody
and there is no competition everybody
wants them to be king in the world
that's some kind of extraordinary good
karma in their past lives
okay and in this life unanimously
i remember ken rinpoche my lama when he
went
he was uh he didn't want to be
a abbot of of our monastery
a it's one of the grade three
monasteries
of tibet he did not want to be of it and
and
he he was too busy he didn't want to get
stuck with this job
and so he kept writing every four years
when they
voted for six years when they voted for
the abbott he sent the paper and said i
will not
accept the abbot position you know
and then he got to be 75 or something
70 years old and he said well okay i
don't have to write this
letter anymore they're not going to do
it now and then they voted him in
because he didn't send the letter and
then he had to do it i i was there when
he
accepted the position and he had to
accept it
and uh so he was uh
he was like i'll accept the position
if the vote is unanimous you know
if if 3 000 monks if there's not
one monk who votes against me i will
accept the position
you know and i was like rinpoche come on
this is a
you know it's never gonna happen
you know and and one guy said he didn't
want
repertoire one guy you know and uh
of course the peer pressure was pretty
intense and
finally he changed his mind but why am i
saying that
that's the karma of a real emperor
that the vote if you run for president
of america the vote will be 350 million
to zero
uh because of your karma you have
intense karma
okay it'll be similar to rinpoche
becoming abbott of absurd of me okay
uh samba gyajin so they have this karma
that powerful beings in the universe
want to protect them and we have a
picture here
of some i like this picture this is a
real bodyguard picture
okay you're right
these guys they're supposed to be secret
service but that you could tell them
immediately you know because of the
sunglasses right
uh and the thing in their ear you know
and if you want to really get some
attention
tim from girls you know just get these
glasses and put the thing in your ear
and walk around and people will think
you're
some high james bond guy or something
anyway uh the karma
of a person who has
heavy heavy good karma from their past
life
and for example is born into a country
where no one starves uh for the first
time in history
okay uh
it's the nature of the universe
that powerful beings want to be their
bodyguards
and they are around you all the time
they are protecting you all the time if
if you
have the karma for example to be born
to come to thine mountain if you have
the karma to reach them
in this life then you already have these
people around you
you don't see them but there are beings
hanging around deflecting problems from
you
already and you don't know you never
know
but there's already powerful beings
protecting you
and they they are not necessarily
buddhists they can be buddhist but
sometimes they're just interested super
powerful
bodyguard beings okay and he lists them
here
so world emperors have these guys
and you don't see them invisible
bodyguards
who keep deflecting problems
the problems you never know you were
supposed to have
there's a lot okay and these guys have
been deflecting them
for you for example if you ever did a
three retreated diamond
you are got a lot of these guys okay
then
he says here if you get bodhichitta
you get double duty
yeah this the home office assigns double
bodyguards for you compared to a world
emperor
okay compared to a king of the world
who has already probably thousands of
invisible bodyguards bodhisattvas
get double okay you have 2 000
invisible bodyguards taking care of you
if you have
bodhichitta if you've tried to have this
motivation
there are invisible powerful beings
deflecting problems from you and you
don't even know because the problems
never
reach you problems that never happened
okay
that was supposed to happen okay
nigeria means a hundred percent more
niger means double ki ninten kundu
day and night they are on duty they are
never off duty okay
somewhere gear way nepa dong they
prevent
problems in your life dun dun they
evil spirits from reaching you geek so
they stop obstacles in your life
problems okay they blocked them and you
don't even know that you were supposed
to have them okay
if you have bought each other all right
young jimmy if you don't have
bodhichitta
and you do kangso so kangso is like
sojou
but it's two parts kang and soul so
kang means to collect new good karma
soul means to fix
old bad karmas and it's similar to
sojourn but it's more powerful
it's a tantric surgeon okay it's called
kangso
and and uh many of the colleges of
of a great monastery like sarah will
will do
kung song once a month they have their
own kang so ceremonies
that are written for their college and
their particular
protector deity which is not the bad
protector
which is argument about it nowadays but
every
major college has their own protector
which everyone agrees is a nice
protector
okay uh kang
and he says you can go take all the guys
in your college
you can go to your college temple you
can get all the big drums
and you can call the protectors uh
at your monthly uh
tantric sojourn right uh
and they won't come if you don't have
buddies okay they won't come okay
join me during 8th amendments we don't
know they're going to come or not
if the guys who are doing the sojourn
ceremony
the purification ceremony don't have
chira you can bang on the drums
you can ring the bells you can do the
mantras
but there's no guarantee that anyone's
going to come to help you
the protectors might listen and they
might not listen okay
the good protectors uh stem de kena
gyaabo nam to say so gil chandeshi
chanma jan kyung
but if you have bodhichitta then even
the highest
of the protectors the example here is
the four great kings
such as vaishravana who are very
powerful
buddhist protectors okay
they will come to protect you as if they
were your
employees okay
you know like you say hey you know hello
where's my coffee you know and they're
like yes sir you know
there's huge dangerous protectors
they're like become your employees okay
you can say hey where
is it you know i don't know
how come there's traffic this morning
what's what are you guys doing
and then oh i'm so sorry you know they
clear all the traffic
you know on the way to tucson or
something okay
that's their job right so they kind of
at your back and calm
okay all right i like to uh say i i was
thinking that uh
nowadays we're trying to practice
medicine buddha many people are
trying to practice medicine kind of as a
team we're trying to do medicine buddha
now there's supposed to be 12 yaksa
generals like very powerful
protector military
dharma military general who's supposed
to help us
and you can apply this to those 12 also
if you if your motivation for medicine
buddhist practice
is to help other people then those 12
spirit generals will come and help you
and they will help you achieve your
projects like building stupas
but if you don't have buddy cheddar and
you call them
with a mantra maybe they won't come
okay there's no guarantee that they will
come
because there's a weird thing they say
people with body children smell good to
them
you know which i guess means if you
don't have bodhichitta
it's you smell like you didn't take a
bath for two weeks or something
okay something like that like they're
attracted
the 12 yaksas are attracted
to people who are wearing that cologne
of bodhichitta and and then they come
even you don't
ask them to come they will come okay
then if you ask them to come but you
you don't care about other people
they're like
you know i don't know you know i'll come
tomorrow maybe
okay all right all right uh
i have this idea i like this picture
it's a fire alarm
and uh long
many years ago i think if people were in
the first aci classes in new york
uh i had this
uh idea of a
very dishonest person what do you call
it
a cynical person unhappy person
who want to make money and so they
they start a company and they start
selling fire extinguishers
that they know don't work okay that
don't work
so you know try to imagine something
more
mean or cynical
than trying to make money by selling
fire extinguishers that you know they
don't work
you know so you kind of
somebody will die from the thing you're
making
that doesn't work and you know it
doesn't work or you don't you don't know
it works and it doesn't work
so i think the point is to do
practices buddhist practices
without bodhichitta and to teach them to
other people
is like selling fire extinguishers that
might not work or fire alarms that might
not work
and then someone's gonna get hurt you
know someone's gonna get hurt
to teach somebody a ritual or a mantra
and then don't teach them lamrim
and don't teach them about bodhichitta
then it's kind of like giving somebody a
fire alarm
that doesn't work or might not work and
if it doesn't work then someone's going
to get hurt right
so that's what they're talking about
here
so what's a safe thing to do to make
sure it works
just be nice to people okay do your
practice for other people
okay if you do your practice for other
people does that mean you're not doing
it for yourself
you you are when you say all living
beings
guess who's one of them
[Music]
people forget that it's so funny i'm
doing this for all living beings
except me why not do it for you too
you're also a living being okay so don't
forget
when you're practicing bodhichitta for
all living beings
my lama used to say duh you're also one
of them
you know you can do prayers for yourself
that's okay
you're also suffering being we're not
leaving you
out okay that'd be so funny okay
you have to love yourself also
you owe yourself love because you are a
suffering living being
simple you don't have to be lovable you
have to be unlovable
then you deserve love okay all right
uh donate i love this sutra
every time we have a quotation from it
it's beautiful
this is the one called the
the house and the jewel forest the house
inside the
the house inside the circle of trees
made of ruby and emerald and
sapphire trees made of emerald
and that's the name of this uh sutra
uh number me dumb see and it's a long
it's a it's kind of a long sentence but
what it means is
in ancient india there were
what do you call that
you put stuff in a little bag and you
carried around your neck
like the native american amulet but what
if you put some kind of uh
herbs a medicine bag or something and
you tie it around your neck
and then there's certain diseases you
cannot get
it's like a vaccination like nowadays
they call it a vaccination
in the old days you put some herbs in a
bag and you tie it around your neck
and you and that will protect you from
certain diseases
okay and there's a list of them in the
sutras
so one of them is called the nabamiduezi
which means
no suffering herb bag and if you wear
that one
there's certain problems and sicknesses
that you can't cannot get if you wear
that medicine bag
on your neck or on your arm or something
see there's another one called the king
of
all elixirs
and if you put that in a medicine bag
and tie it around your neck
do genoa
you will never step on a rattlesnake at
diamond mountain
they don't like it when you get close
they
they go away there's some kind of smell
from the back we should find this one
and see me tupa then there's called the
king of
medicine bags shanghi me tupa
unbeatable okay and
lulachang if you tie that one on your
neck
jamie tupa uh people can never take
advantage of you
okay so these are different medicine
bags that people used to
tie on their necks why is he talking
about this
yeah you want the ultimate medicine bag
then get somebody cheddar and
it repels all problems automatically
okay that's the idea
the ancient sutras talk about
special plants
that you can put in a bag and tie around
your neck
and certain bad things will never happen
to you like snakes biting you
but why not just get titter
and tie that around your neck and then
nothing can hurt you
okay and that's another benefit of
bodhichitta
you become impregnable okay it's like
armor
okay and i have a picture here
of a fact isn't that a cool idea that
if you had a certain kind of motivation
to jump planet it would be
like the covid vaccination
and you would never get certain problems
they just couldn't happen
nowadays you know some of us got our
vaccinations
uh we we were i stayed in my house for a
year i didn't go anywhere
i didn't go i like i needed something
from the hardware store
i needed a little thing from my garden i
called them you know i said do you
deliver they said
yeah what do you need i said i need a
water sprinkler
it's ten dollars right and they said
okay
i said can you deliver it yeah it's a
hundred dollars
to deliver it you know i said what
hundred dollars to deliver a ten dollar
spickler
yeah i said i'll take it
you know i was like damn i can get my
car and go buy it
in in 10 minutes or 15 minutes but i
don't want to die
you know it's not worth it i'll pay the
hundred dollars you know
then then they give you a vaccination
and it's so cool you know now we go to
coffee shops
i went to san diego i went to a nice
beach
i went surfing for a week every morning
i went to
get this waffles
and i was like no man
you know and uh that's a vaccination
you know so bodhi chitta
is the ultimate vaccination you don't
have to wear a mask
if you have bodhichitta i mean you
should right still wear a mouth
you should wear a mask i have my mask
right here
but you should wear it and thank you
i really do here i have to prove it no
so i still wear it but what i'm saying
is
if you get a real vaccination called
bodhichitta
you don't have to worry about other
things it protects you
i'm not saying you shouldn't wear a mask
i'm not saying you shouldn't get a
vaccination
what i'm saying is if you have
bodhichitta your mask will work
and your vaccination will work which you
should still get
or you should still wear okay good
all right i went and found the quotation
from the sutra if you're interested i'll
give it to you someday
it's long and boring and we don't know
what those bags were anyway
we don't know what was in them anymore
so okay
now they're going to talk about geshe
kamloomba and and i had a
teacher named kamloom a great rinpoche
common
and this is a kadampa geshe from a
thousand years ago
geshe kamloomba he was
meditating on bodhichitta
in the mountains of a place called
in a state called pimple which
produces some cool llamas i i've had
some llamas from pimple
uh chan sam gomshin shuka you de me
mayin namki
then there were some evil spirits living
in pimbo at that time and like we used
to have them around here and then
negative spirits you know probably
people who are upset because they were
killed here
[Music]
he was meditating on bodhichitta
in his retreat cabin and the retreat
cavern was surrounded by
negative spirits okay and they said well
let's go get him you know
let's go get this guy let's ruin his
retreat
you know let's make sure the plumbing
breaks
just when he starts his retreat if
you've ever tried to do retreats
there's a about a million different
things
one day i did a retreat in
a cicada
plague happened thousands of
grasshoppers going really around the
cabin
and then they kind of flew away and then
i found out the cabin was next to a
peacock farm
and peacocks go wrong all day long
and anyway if you want to have obstacles
try to do a retreat right
okay why are we talking about that this
geshi kamalumba was trying to do a
retreat and these
demons said let's go get him you know
let's go ruin his regime
okay then one of them said
ah it's not working out you know
it's not working out we're trying to
ruin his retreat
we're trying to disturb his retreat but
it's not working out
what's the problem you know what's
stopping us
and one of them said he loves us more
than himself
he cares for us more than he cares for
himself
we can't touch him you can't touch him
you know
that's so cool you know let's ruin his
retreat
yeah it's not working out why ah
he loves us more than he loves himself
how can we hurt
we can't hurt him we keep trying and
nothing happens you know
he loves us people always ask me by the
way
uh lots of people in our group try to do
retreats
medicine benefits very cool and
uh you always have problems you know you
always get some
you know problems happen uh in retreats
and and i think not a few of us
uh believe that we have seen the
experience during a deep retreat like
i it's happened to me twice in
in 40 years okay
but i i think i have seen those spirits
and uh
and then and then people ask me what
should i do i have a spirit in my
in my retreat cabin in the one that i
one of the ones i s
one of the ones i saw looked like a good
friend of mine
and one of the ones i saw looked like uh
black
ink uh flowing uh
between the wall and the ceiling
and and disturbing the retreat you know
and uh
so people ask me do you believe in those
spirits and i say well i
i haven't i didn't grow up
in a country where my parents talked
about these spirits
we thought it was superstition so no i
didn't grow up
believing in spirits in those spirits
but i experienced them a few times
and then i asked my teacher what should
i do
you know what what can i do you know how
do i get him out of my retreat kevin
and he said love them they can't stand
it
no no he said just love them you know
and make friends with them take care of
them
support them welcome evil spirit
to my retreat cabin would you like some
tormas
or are you guys hungry or are people
ignoring you
uh the most frustrating thing for evil
spirit is when people don't believe they
like yeah we're here you want us to
prove it
so how to deal with uh
almost supernatural obstacles
they are also living beings they are
also people
and they also need love and they also
respond to love
everyone responds to love so
love them and tell them you love them
and show them you love them
go pick some flowers for them and put
them on the altar and say these are
these are for you guys not for the
buddhas
okay these are for you guys okay and and
that's how to deal with them okay
all right
by the way uh in the scripture here
in the long rim that geshe kamloomba
is that the demons call him
a name they're trying to think of an
insulting name
to give him and they say he's just like
doctor
sarah
the bodhisattva who can't stop crying so
he came again this buddhism came again
that's why you have to be a volunteer
for aci
because you get to hear the story of the
bodhisattva
okay so this demons were calling him
names you know
and they're kind of yeah just like that
guy and he can't stop crying you're
stupid
the accuser it's the biggest insult they
could think of
you know you're just like that
bodhisattva from the 8000 verses
okay all right shin dupe never kill me
put we can't hurt him
all the stuff we're trying to do to hurt
this guy doesn't work okay
chain made so all right made soul means
uh
our lama taught us how he said that okay
so a lot of times you'll see the
the incomparable tj rinpoche who's
writing the transcript will report what
islam said okay
do mark zumba and there's also the
there's also the precedent
of how our lord buddha dealt with
the obstacles that were presented to him
especially the famous ones
are in the moment of his enlightenment
what's the story
yeah they threw spears and they shot
bows and arrows
and then his love for them
turned them into flowers
in midair that's such a cool idea
like it doesn't take very long for an
arrow to go from me to cat
cutting but then imagine it turning to a
flower halfway
so i shoot an arrow at her because i'm
angry and then
a flower incoming incoming flower
whatever and this is a big rose
big rose okay so there's the president
uh lord buddha how did he react
to evil spirits somehow he
loved them so deeply that their weapons
became flowers
and i think if you try it with people in
your life
who cause you problems you will have the
same experience you know
if you try to love them what's the best
way
to deal with an irritating person
in your life is to love them
and then the spears will change to
flowers okay
what's the best way to deal with a
problem person
is love them okay by the way that
doesn't mean
you cannot discipline them or you know
spank them if they're bad okay but
with love because you love them
all right
then there's a story about a tibetan
king
who because he had so much love
for everyone all the negative spirits
in his country couldn't hurt
people okay the king set
such a good example of loving people who
caused him trouble
that when the demons tried to hurt the
country
the economy of the country which is a
yak hurting
it didn't work okay there's this
guy what's his name richard kramer i
forget
bishop uh in in london
who helped write the church of england's
purple it's it's an extraordinary
prayer book extraordinary there was
many people thought it was written by
shakespeare and
uh there was a joke that uh
what was that if you want to
get fed for the rest of your life
become his enemy because he will take
care of you for the rest of your life
it was a very beautiful story this
bishop was so
loving to his enemies that the way to
get
a lifetime pension was to try to hurt
him
and then he would take care of you for
the rest of your life
you know it's really cool okay all right
that's the best way to deal with problem
people
tim when should i stop five minutes from
now
okay and we're gonna have a special
question from a person who won the
lottery yesterday
and then we're gonna have another
lottery for tomorrow okay good
we have time to do this last spirit
story
this spirit is called behar okay
and tibet has
lots of local spirits in those
mysterious mountains
before buddhism came after buddhism came
a lot of them became buddhist protectors
good guys okay
[Music]
there was one named behar
and
he came to bhutan rinpoche butter
rinpoche lived just before tsonkapa
and he's famous for
he wrote a history of buddhism very
famous and
yeah he he organized the kanye and the
tenure he organized the
three 4 600 books from ancient india
got the translations all done got them
into their current form
mostly okay and then there was another
llama named sunum gilten
at the same in the same period just
before tonka
and this demon offered them an iron
nuku nuku means bamboo shoot
which came to mean pen
and and he offered them an iron pen
why would a demon offer two eminent
llamas
a pen
yeah exactly it's like giving that a
computer
and he was trying to disturb their
meditation practice
okay he was trying to get them to write
books all day
and not do their meditation okay and he
succeeded
okay he was able that demon
was able to offer an iron pen
meaning a computer okay to these two
llamas
but okay but muchu
so muchu means quicksilver and there's
we have a famous
two two famous quicksilver llamas in our
vajrayogini but it's a place name
quicksilver is a place name and there
was another famous bodhisattva
from that same quicksilver
county called togmei
who wrote a famous commentary to master
shanti deva
and when the demon came to him to offer
him a computer
it kept falling or it kept he kept
losing it
got it why yeah his bony chitta
protected him from
these distractions okay probably he
would have tried to buy an iphone and it
would probably keep breaking
and then he'd have to meditate because
he didn't have anything else to do
okay so he had the he had the power of
bodhichitta
that prevented uh people from
destructing him demons from destruction
so whole point is
by the way we have a picture right paul
where's that guy is it no
i got one bef before that i think
yeah how to how to ruin a kid's life
give him a ipad pad you know
how to ruin a a kid how to get a kid
to ignore the entire
world of nature is to give them a
four-inch piece of glass that they can
spend their whole life in
and not enjoy the world
okay so you can do the same thing with
children right
give them a little piece of glass
where they can see pictures of deer and
trees and sky and
never experience deer and trees and
skies so anyway
all right tim so anyway you can protect
yourself
from these negative influences including
too much computer
some computer is very useful john
brady's computer project is
very important but too much computer can
be an
obstacle and if you
have love those obstacles will not
appear in your life
okay miss